Guide to the Arthur Howe Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur Howe Jr. papers
1857-2012
MS 1755
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.17
(22 Boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and general files that document Arthur Howe Jr.'s service as Yale admissions dean, tenure on the Board of Directors of Hampton Institute, and family history.
Howe, Arthur Jr.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arthur Howe Jr., 1999 and 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
The bulk of the materials are open for research. Accession 2018-M-0015 contains two student papers which are restricted until 1 January 2087 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and one addition:
I. Hampton Institute Files, 1902-1997.
II. Family Papers, 1857-1969.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Howe, Jr. was born on July 19, 1921 in Watertown, Connecticut. He entered Yale University with the Class of 1943, obtaining a B.A. in 1947 after serving in the military during the Second World War. Howe held several administrative positions at Yale College, including assistant dean of freshman (1951-1953), director of admissions (1953-1955), and dean of admissions and student appointments (1955-1964). Beginning in 1964, Howe served as the president of the American Field Service. From 1955 to 1980, Howe also served on the board of trustees of Hampton Institute, which his grandfather, Samuel Chapman Armstrong, founded and his father, Arthur Howe, Sr., served as president. Howe was chair of the Hampton Institute board of trustees from 1957 to 1971. Arthur Howe, Jr. died in Essex, Connecticut on December 16, 2014.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and general files that document Arthur Howe Jr.'s service as Yale College admissions dean, tenure on the board of trustees of Hampton Institute, and family history. The collection includes an unpublished history of Hampton Institute by Edward Kidder Graham, articles and student papers on the history of Yale College admissions, and unpublished autobiographical writings and correspondence by Howe's grandfather, Samuel Chapman Armstrong.
African Americans -- Education (Higher); Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877); Universities and colleges, Black; Armstrong, S. C. (Samuel Chapman), 1839-1893; Howe, Arthur Jr.; Howe, Arthur, 1890-1955; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Hampton Institute
- Hampton Institute Files, 1902-1997
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, Hampton Institute (HI) Files include correspondence, memoranda, clippings, minutes, reports and other materials documenting Albert Howe Jr.'s tenure on the Board of Trustees of Hampton Institute, which he served from 1955 to 1980. As a member and chair (1957-1971) of the board, Howe was involved in and/or informed of many facets of the administration of Hampton, and the records in this series give substantive and substantial documentation of the school during this time period.
  Nine folders of general correspondence are listed at the beginning of the series and arranged chronologically, but correspondence of a topical nature is interspersed throughout the records. Howe also kept separate files of correspondence and other materials for the presidents of Hampton with whom he served, including William Harvey, Jerome Holland, Roy Hudson, and Alonzo Moron, although letters to and from these men can also be found among the general correspondence. The general correspondence also includes letters to and from other Hampton officials and board members, including the anthropologist Margaret Mead, who served on the board with Howe. Other Mead materials are commingled among the Board of Trustees and "Howe Memorandum" sections of the series.
  The bulk of the other records fall under one of the following headings: Board of Trustees; the "Howe Memorandum," and Graham, Edward Kidder. The most substantive records documenting the work of the Board of Trustees are located in the meetings and committee records. Other board materials are listed under the "Howe Memorandum." In 1976, Howe drafted a memorandum proposing that Hampton reorient its programs and mission towards the establishment of an academically rigorous preparatory school, aimed at readying African-American youth for admission to competitive colleges and universities. The idea was met with resistance and caused great controversy. The section includes materials that document the development of and reaction to the memorandum.
  In the late 1960s, Edward Kidder Graham was commissioned to write a history of Hampton, which was not subsequently published. Filed under Graham, the series includes two drafts of the work, along with correspondence and research materials that give detailed information on the history of the institute.
  - General correspondence, 1959-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Academic affairs committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Academic appeals, 1960, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ad hoc committee on athletics, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ad hoc task force on non-traditional self study, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Benton, William, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Black power and black identification [Hampton Institute position paper; includes correspondence with the NAACP], 1965-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of Trustees
    General note
    See:
    Series I, folder 163
    - Bylaws, 1970, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Committees
      - Executive, 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17-21)
      - Faculty/Board relationships, 1959-1980 (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
      - Investment
        - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
        - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
        - Special report on the permanent endowment investment record from 1944 to 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Nominating, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Student relationships, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
    - Financial contributions from members, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Mailing lists and membership, 1955-1984 (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
    - Meetings [includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and reports], 1959-1979 June (Box 3, Folder 41-46)
    - Meetings [includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and reports], 1979 October-1980 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
    - Photographs
    - Retreat, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Trusteeship (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Bodein, Vernon [minister of Hampton Institute], 1970 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Budget and finance committee, 1960, 1961, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Buildings and grounds, 1958, 1961, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Camper, M. Arthur [minister of Hampton Institute], 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Centennial Medallion Citation, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Chambers, Dwight [chair of Medieval Languages, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Committee on the instruction program, 1956-1979 (Box 4, Folder 59-62)
  - Convocation [correspondence and publications], 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 63-64)
  - Development, 1974, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Faculty
    - Dismissals, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Resignations, 1957-1975 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Statistics and racial diversity, 1957-1958, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Ford Foundation, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Founder's Day, 1956-1969 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Frissell, Sydney Dodd [essay entitled "Camp Hampton," which recalls the early days of Hampton Institute], undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Graham, Edward Kidder. "A Tender Violence: The Life of Hampton Institute in Relation to its Time" [centennial history of Hampton Institute]
    - First draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 72-77)
    - Final draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 78-84)
    - Correspondence
      See also:
      Series I, folders 59-60
      - General, 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 85-86)
      - Howe, Margaret Armstrong, 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 87-91)
    - Research materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 92-93)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Hampton Institute Commission
    - Charge, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 96-100)
    - Meetings [agendas, minutes, and reports], 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 101-103)
  - Harvey, William [president of Hampton Institute]
    - Clippings, 1978-1991 (Box 8, Folder 104-105)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1988 (Box 8, Folder 106-107)
  - Hill, Carl M., 1976 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - History [correspondence and notes on the history of Hampton Institute], 1962, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Holland, Jerome [president of Hampton Institute]
    - Appointment as ambassador to Sweden, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Inauguration, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Resignation
      - General, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 112)
      - Clippings, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 113)
      - "The Fulfillment of a Pledge: A Decade (1960-1970) at Hampton Institute", 1969 (Box 8, Folder 114)
      - Letters of support, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Honors Day program, 1976, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Hospital board, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - "Howe Memorandum"
    - General [includes the memorandum], 1976 (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - Adams Consultants meeting, 1979, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - Background material
      - Correspondence, 1976-1982 (Box 9, Folder 120)
      - Clippings, 1932, 1976-1997 (Box 9, Folder 121-124)
      - Notes, 1968-1996 (Box 9, Folder 125)
      - Publications, 1975-1996 (Box 9, Folder 126-127)
      - Reports, 1926, 1971-1982 (Box 10, Folder 128-130)
      - Study committee, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 131)
    - Reaction to memorandum
      - Board of Trustees memoranda, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 132)
      - Clippings, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 133)
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 134-136)
      - Notes, 1975-1979 (Box 10, Folder 137)
  - Howe, Arthur Sr. [memorandum on the establishment of a vocational junior college], ca. 1938 (Box 10, Folder 138)
  - Hudson, Roy [president of Hampton Institute]
    - General, 1970-1975 (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - Resignation, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 140)
  - Indiana Conference on Higher Education, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - James Foundation, 1958-1964 (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - Letters of complaint, 1959-1971 (Box 11, Folder 143)
  - Letters of encouragement, 1960-1976 (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Lindsay, Donal, 1970-1986 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Long-range Planning Council, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Martin, William [acting president of Hampton Institute], 1959-1960 (Box 11, Folder 147)
  - Moron, Alonzo G.
    - Resignation
      - Clippings, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 148)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1957-1959 (Box 11, Folder 149-155)
    - Virgin Island Leadership Training Program, 1959-1960 (Box 11, Folder 156)
  - National Hampton Alumni Association, 1959-1962, 1975, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 157)
  - Notes [miscellaneous], 1958, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - "Official Hampton" [publication listing trustees, officers, faculty, student organizations, and enrollment figures], 1958 (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - The Oram Group, 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 160)
  - Patterson, Frederic [proposal to increase school endowment], 1972 (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Photographs
    Series II, folder 58
    - General, 1950, undated (Box 12, Folder 162)
    - Board of Trustees, undated (Box 12, Folder 163)
    - Howe, Arthur Sr., 1937, 1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 164)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 12, Folder 165)
  - President's report, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 166)
  - Price Waterhouse and Co. [fundraising information], 1975-1987 (Box 12, Folder 167)
  - Profile of Hampton Institute, undated (Box 12, Folder 168)
  - Publications, 1956-1989 (Box 12, Folder 169)
  - Retirement of Arthur Howe Jr. as chairman of the Board of Trustees [tributes], 1972 (Box 12, Folder 170-171)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor [visit to Hampton Institute], 1938, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 172)
  - St. Cyprian's Church, 1957-1959 (Box 12, Folder 173)
  - Salary and pension disputes, 1966-1976 (Box 12, Folder 174)
  - Scholarships, 1958-1976 (Box 12, Folder 175)
  - Search committee for president of Hampton Institute, 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 176-178)
  - Secretary of the college, 1961-1967 (Box 12, Folder 179)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1968, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 180)
  - Speeches and notes, 1938-1997 (Box 13, Folder 181-182)
  - Student enrollment, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 183)
  - Student government, 1968-1970 (Box 13, Folder 184)
  - Student protests at Hampton Institute, 1969, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 185-188)
  - Student protests nationwide, 1968-1970 (Box 13, Folder 189-191)
  - Student publications, 1969-1986 (Box 13, Folder 192)
  - Thomas, Edgar R., 1969 (Box 13, Folder 193)
  - Visits to Hampton Institute [correspondence and itineraries], 1962, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 194)
  - White, Alfred T., 1989 (Box 13, Folder 195)
  - Whiteman, Harold B., 1978 (Box 13, Folder 196)
- Family Papers, 1857-1969
  Series II, folder 13
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member, the series includes correspondence (both photocopies and originals), photographs, writings, and other materials primarily documenting the ancestors of Arthur Howe Jr. The most substantial and substantive material relates to Howe's grandfather, Samuel Chapman Armstrong, Civil War general and founder of Hampton Institute. The series includes a small amount of Armstrong's correspondence with family and associates, manuscript and typescript copies of the unpublished "Personal Memories and Letters of General Samuel Chapman Armstrong" (edited posthumously by Helen Ludlow), journal fragments, and other writings.
  The series also holds materials relating to Clarissa Chapman Armstrong (great-grandmother), Arthur Howe Sr., and Margaret Armstrong Howe (mother). Five folders of miscellaneous and unidentified correspondence, clippings, and photographs are listed at the end of the series.
  - Inventory of family papers [prepared by Edward K. Graham], 1969 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, Clarissa Chapman
    Series II, folder 8
    - "Clarissa Chapman Armstrong" [biographical pamphlet by Helen Ludlow], undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence
    - Journal entries [typed transcript of 1831 original], undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Armstrong, Richard
    - Journal entries [typed transcript of 1831-1832 original], undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Photograph and obituary, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Armstrong, Samuel Chapman
    - Correspondence
      - Armstrong, Carrie [sister], 1884, 1890 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Armstrong, Clarissa Chapman, 1885-1888 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Folsom, Cora, 1885 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Foote, Henry W. [includes two letters to Mrs. Foote], 1880-1889 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Gassman, John G., 1885 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Hopkins, Archibald, 1865-1868, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Howe, Albert, 1870, 1891 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - King, Josiah [photocopy], 1867 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Lyons, Lucia, 1890 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Washington, Booker T. [photocopies], 1889, 1892 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Weaver, Ellen Armstrong [includes one letter to Phillip Weaver], 1862, 1881-1891 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - "Impressions of General Armstrong" [written by George Davis, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Journal, 1857-1858 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - "Personal Memories and Letters of General Samuel Chapman Armstrong" [edited by Helen Ludlow]
      - Manuscript
        - Table of contents, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
        - Introduction-Chapter 15, undated (Box 14, Folder 21-28)
        - Chapter 16-22, undated (Box 15, Folder 29-35)
      - Typescript
        - Introduction-Chapter 10, undated (Box 15, Folder 36-39)
        - Chapter 11-22, undated (Box 16, Folder 40-49)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 16, Folder 50)
    - "Reminiscences", undated (Box 16, Folder 51)
    - Testimonials, 1886-1893 (Box 16, Folder 52)
  - Hawaiian Mission Children's Society [includes photocopies of letters from 1848 and 1867 detailing the family's missionary work in Hawaii], 1967, undated (Box 16, Folder 53)
  - Howe, Albert, 1890, 1891 (Box 17, Folder 54)
  - Howe, Arthur Sr.
    Series I, folder 164
    - "Address at Meeting of the Boston Chapter of the N.A.A.C.P.", 1936 (Box 17, Folder 55)
    - Clippings, 1936, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 56)
    - Memorabilia, 1916 (Box 17, Folder 57)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 17, Folder 58)
  - Howe, Margaret Armstrong
    Series I, folders 87-91
    - Correspondence [primarily with Suzanne Carlson and Sydney Frissell], 1950-1966, undated (Box 17, Folder 59-60)
    - Writings, 1913 (Box 17, Folder 61)
  - Scoville, Samuel A. [correspondence relating to other Armstrong family related materials], 1953 (Box 17, Folder 62)
  - Clippings [miscellaneous], 1966, undated (Box 17, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence [unidentified and miscellaneous], 1894, 1931-1940, undated (Box 17, Folder 64-65)
  - Photographs [unidentified and miscellaneous], undated (Box 17, Folder 66-67)
- Additional Material, 1890-2012; Accession 2018-M-0015; 2.17; (4 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research. Two student papers on Yale College admissions and coeducation are restricted until 1 January 2087 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
  Arrangement
  The accession is arranged into five groupings: Yale College admissions, correspondence, Hampton Institute files, research files and talks, and personal files.
  The accession contains material documenting Arthur Howe's career in Yale College admissions, including his efforts to introduce coeducation to Yale undergraduates and admit a more diverse student body. Contains articles and two student essays on the history of admissions at Yale. Also includes material on the Hampton Institute, which was founded by Howe's grandfather, Samuel Chapman Armstrong, as well as citations from the Hampton Institute and the Commonwealth of Virginia for Arthur Howe Jr., as well as his father, Arthur Howe Sr., and his mother, Margaret Howe.
  - Yale College admissions
    - Antisemitism, Jewish enrollment at Yale College, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Articles, 1956-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Coeducation, 1956-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General files, 1954-2012 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
    - Notes on Southern Rhodesia interviews, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Selection- admissions and information, 2003-2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Student papers on Yale College admissions and coeducation, 1990-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      Student records are restricted until 1 January 2087 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
  - Correspondence
    - Cory, Christopher, 2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Department of Education (Civil Rights), 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Farrell, Gregory, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kabaservice, Geoffrey, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Sleeper, Jim, 2003-2012 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hampton Institute files
    - Citation for Margaret A. Howe, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Citation presenting Arthur Howe Jr. as a candidate for the honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Citations for Arthur Howe Jr., 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Early photographs, Circa 1890s (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hampton Alumni Record, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Howe, Arthur, Jr. file, 1976-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Howe, Arthur, Sr., acceptance as president of institute, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Howe, Arthur, Sr., resignation, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research files and talks
    - Affirmative Action, 1982-2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - In Memory of our Beloved Nellie P. Elliott, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Why Pomfret?, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal
    - Citation for Arthur Howe Sr., representative to The Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Citation for Arthur Howe Sr., to represent Virginia at National Negro Day at California Pacific International Exposition, San Diego, California, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Howe, Arthur, Jr., personal letters, 1941-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Yale College and state house print, Circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Yale College class of 1961 50th reunion, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 7)